All right, בוקר טוב boqer tov everybody. We pick up at the
bottom, we pick up at the bottom of צדיק ח' עמוד א',
Tzaddik Chet Amud Aleph, today's דף daf
is officially צדיק ט', Tzaddik Tet, but we're a little bit behind.
Quiet please on the set, quiet on the set, we're filming. Okay
so four, three lines from the bottom, we're dealing with the question
about whether after conversion a גר ger can marry his biological
brother's wife.
But, so we're bringing various evidence to it, most of the evidence
points to yes, but the גמרא Gemara is finding ways out of
it. תא שמע, Ta shema, come in here, three lines from the
bottom. We read what we did at the end of yesterday. Okay,
גר שהייתה לידתו בקדושה והורתו שלא בקדושה, Ger shehaysa lidaso bikdusha vehoraso
shelo bikdusha, blah blah
blah, גר
שהייתה לידתו בקדושה והורתו שלא
בקדושה
Ger shehaysa lidaso bikdusha
vehoraso shelo bikdusha who was conceived of when his mother had
not converted, born after his mother was converted. יש לו שאר האם,
Yesh lo shear ha'em, there's still an issue about marrying a relative
on the mother's side, ואין לו שאר האב v'ein lo shear ha'av
on the father's side. כיצד, Keitzad, what's the story? נשא אחותו מן
האם יוציא. Nasa achoso min ha'em yotzi. If he marries his sister
on his mother's side, this would be a sister who was born
when his mother was not Jewish, so legally they're not married, biologically
obviously they are.
Not what I say Jewish, legally they're not related, biologically they are.
So he has to divorce her. מן האב, Min ha'av, if it
was somebody who was related only on the father's side and not
Jewish, and again legally not related, biologically they are, יקיים, yeka'yeim, he
can keep her. So first of all, that's interesting that even though
clearly it's biological incest, we're not bothered with it, but we are
bothered with the case on the mother's side. Why? Because as we've
been seeing, on the mother's side is more evidently or it's more
perceived of by people as being a relation. Now there's a whole
discussion in רש"י Rashi and
תוספות Tosafot
about what exactly the reason for this is. רש"י Rashi says it's
more of a גזירה gezeira of a concern that if we allow
this for him to maintain his sister from beforehand, he'll come to
marry his sister who'll be born afterwards, and that will be legally
his sister. תוספות Tosafot says that's not the concern, that תוספות Tosafot
basically just says like similar issues that we had before, that it
just looks like something that is inherently proper, like people will think,
oh look, a brother is marrying his
sister.
Well, but yeah, but again, that's a concern particularly when it's on
the mother's side, because that's as we've been discussing before, that people
do perceive of as being related, but it's not a גזירה. gezeira.
And תוספות Tosafot discusses what some of the implications of that are.
Okay, now אחות האב מן האם יוציא, Achot ha'av min ha'em yotzi,
if it is his father's sister, which is one of the עריות,
arayos, if it's his father's sister on the mother's side, meaning the
father and sister are siblings through the mother, and again these are
non-Jews, his father, his father's sister, but let's say then she converted
or whatever, but they were born as non-Jews, יוציא, yotzi, has to
divorce again since it's a relationship that emerges through the mother, although
interestingly, the father-sister relationship is that they're siblings by the mother, but
it is through his father. רש"י, Rashi, I'll just tell you the
way רש"י Rashi reads it, is that here since it's still a
case of sister, and sister on the mother's side, if we allow
this, it'll come to a case of his sister on the mother's
side, it's all part of the same package.
We didn't say that before with marrying a sister on the father's
side,
it'll come to marry a sister on the mother's side.
I know, because here the sibling relationship is through the mother. מן
האב, Min ha'av, if it is the father's sister and the father
and the sister
are paternal siblings, יקיים, yeka'yeim, then that's not a problem. Okay? So
the same thing that's true about his sibling, that it's a problem
on the mother's side, is true about a father's sibling.
Even through a grandmother or grandfather.
No, it is, what do you mean מן האם? min ha'em? And,
but is it aunt, is his father related to his aunt, is
it a maternal sibling or paternal sibling? Okay? So and that's we're
just extending the same thing that's true about his sister, that it's
only true if it's a maternal sibling, the same is true about
a father's sister. Again, even though this is through the father, the
way רש"י Rashi explains it, it makes a certain amount of sense,
because it starts out dealing with siblings, maternal siblings as opposed to
paternal siblings, even though this is through the father, it's still a
problem. אחות האם מן האם יוציא, Achot ha'em min ha'em yotzi, so
then this should be obvious, a mother's sister which is a maternal
sibling, יוציא, yotzi, that's obvious. מן האב, Min ha'av, so now this
is interesting, this is like the mirror case of the one right
before it. If it's a mother's sister,
but the mother is related to her sister through their father, so
it's a paternal sister. Okay? So here again, it's like one mother,
one father in the mix, a mother and a grandfather in the
mix, but nevertheless the sibling relationship is a paternal one. And until
now paternal siblings we have not been bothered with. רבי מאיר אומר
יוציא, Rabbi Meir omer yotzi, you have to divorce. He still says
too bad since it starts with a mother. חכמים אומרים יקיים *Chachamim
omrim yekayem*, we don't have to worry about it. שרבי מאיר אומר
*She-Rabbi Meir omer*, כל ערווה שמשום שאר האם יוציא משום האב יקיים
*kol ervah shemishum sheer ha'em yotzi, mishum ha'av yekayem* because Rabbi Meir
says as long as there's a mother somewhere somehow involved in the
mix, you have to divorce. Okay, so that's all very confusing about
siblings and aunts, but the basic point is is it a problem
if it's a maternal sibling, if it's not a problem if it's
paternal, and we sort of extend that one generation up as well
in terms of a mother or father sibling. All right, and again,
is that because of a concern of what will happen after this
person was born, that then if we allow this, we'll allow a
similar thing after the person is born, or is it just a
concern that even forgetting about what will happen after, right now it
looks like he's marrying his sibling, and again with the idea that
a sibling on the mother's side is something that people much more
perceive of as a sibling, although in all these cases legally they're
not related. All right, so that's about the sibling. Not exactly our
case yet. Now we start to hone into our case. ומותר באשת
אחיו מאמו ובאשת אחי אביו *umutar be-eshet achiv me-imo u-ve-eshet achi aviv*,
he is allowed to marry his brother's, his maternal brother's wife. So
this is exactly our question: can he marry his maternal brother's wife?
And this baraita says yes. Even though he can't marry his maternal
sister, he can marry his maternal brother's wife. This is less serious
because, again, although they may be perceived of as siblings, again, because
it's like not exactly a blood relation, we are being more lenient.
ובאשת אחי אביו *u-be-eshet achi aviv*, and he also is allowed to
marry his uncle's wife, again because it's through a marriage and it's
not a blood relation. ושאר כל העריות מותרות לו *v-shaar kol arayot
mutarot lo*, and all other prohibited, all other incestuous relationships are permissible
to him, other than sort of sister and aunt. What are we
dealing with other than sister and aunt? לאתויי אשת האב *l-atuyei eshet
ha-av*, for example, others that have to do with through marriage, like
his father's, who's not Jewish, remember, his father, who's not legally his
father, his father's wife. Okay. נשא אשה ובתה *nasa isha u-vittah*, if
before he had converted, he was married to a woman and her
daughter, כונס אחת ומוציא אחת *kones achat u-motzi achat*, now that he's
converted, he can keep one of them and has to divorce the
other, because he can't be married to both. Although, again, if they
both converted with him, they are no longer mother and daughter, right?
Got the scenario? Right, they converted with him, they're no longer mother
and daughter, so you could say, well, why not marry both? But
it's similar again, here is a case of blood relation, biological and
mother, right? So everybody perceives it as such. So in this case,
we do not allow that and he can only be married to
one of them.
Okay, so כונס אחת ומוציא אחת *kones achat u-motzi achat*. לכתחילה לא
יכנוס *l-chat-chila lo yichnos*, he can't do it lechatchila. The Gemara will
sort of say that's obvious, because he just said he even has
to divorce one anyway. מתה אשתו מותר בחמותו *metah ishto mutar be-chamoto*,
and although we said that he cannot marry mother and daughter who
had both converted, if one of them dies, let's say he's married
the younger one, he can marry her mother, although halakhically a person
cannot marry a woman's, his wife's mother or daughter even after his
wife dies, here we will allow it because, again, legally the mother
and daughter are not related, they had both converted. All right, so
that's a lot of information. We're going to hone in though on
the part that's relevant to us. קתני מיהת ומותר באשת אחיו *katani
mihat u-mutar
be-eshet achiv* ואיכא דתני אסור בחמותו *v-ika de-tani asur be-chamoto* and
some say that even after his wife died, he can't marry her
non-halakhic mother, her biological but not halakhic mother. קתני מיהת *katani mihat*
we taught nonetheless, ומותר באשת אחיו *u-mutar be-eshet achiv* that he's allowed
to marry brother's wife, which is exactly our question, even maternal brother's
wife. So, מאי לאו דנסבו כשהוא גר *mai lav de-nasvu k-shehu ger*,
it must be the case, as we went to yesterday, that this
is of course the obvious scenario, that his brother married after he
had converted and it was legally his brother's wife, but this guy
is not legally his brother even though it is his maternal brother.
So you see that's our case and it must... לא דנסבו כשהוא
עכו"ם *lo de-nasvu k-shehu akum*, no, it was a woman that his
brother had been married to when he was not Jewish, and then
he, and then the brother and he converted, and therefore the brother's
no longer even married to her, or was never, excuse me, was
never married to her as a Jew. Okay, so Gemara again says
like it said yesterday, מאי למימרא *mai l-meimra*, so then what's the
chiddush? No, מהו דתימא *mahu d-teima*, I might have thought, ליגזר כשהוא
עכו"ם אטו otu כשהוא גר *ligzor k-shehu akum atu k-shehu ger*, let's
make say that we won't allow him to marry this woman he
was married to as a non-Jew, their brother was married to as
a non-Jew, because then we'll lead to allowing him to marry the
woman the brother was married to as a Jew. קמשמע לן *kamashma
lan* that we're not concerned. So that's how he's gotten out of
all the cases, saying that it's only brother's wife where brother had
been married to as a non-Jew, but again, the simple evidence of
all these cases is that there is not a concern with brother's
wife of two brothers who convert.
When he's married to this woman as a non-Jew, then he converted,
then at what point in the process did she convert?
Presumably same time, but they never,
they didn't
do a new kiddushin, and now the other brother says, hey, let's
get married. אמר מר *amar mar*, now let's just wrap up this
baraita. נשא אשה ובתה כונס אחת ומוציא אחת לכתחילה לא יכנוס *nasa
isha u-vittah kones achat u-motzi achat l-chat-chila lo yichnos*, so he and
a woman and her daughter convert, marry one, divorce the other, but
don't do it lechatchila. Gemara says השתא מפיק מפיק *hashtah mafik mafik*,
if he has to divorce one of them, לכתחילה מיבעיא *l-chat-chila mibaya*,
of course you can't lechatchila do it. התם קאי *Hatam kai*, it's
not going on the immediately on the immediate case of mother and
daughter, it's going on the earlier cases, והכי קאמר *vehachi ka-amar*, and
this is what it's saying: הך דאמרי רבנן קאי *hach de-amrei Rabbanan
kai*, the things that the Rabbis said you can keep the marriage,
for example, the case about a paternal sister, okay, לכתחילה לא יכנוס
*lechatchila lo yichnos*, even though we said that you can do it
בדיעבד *be-di'avad*, you can keep it, don't go ahead and do it
לכתחילה *lechatchila*, even something like a paternal sister. All right, so now
going on to the next part of the ברייתא Braisa. *Baraita*: מתה
אשתו מותר בחמותו *mesa ishto mutar be-chamoso*, after the wife died, he
can marry her mother, her biological mother, although again they converted so
they're not legally related. ואיכא דאמרי אסור בחמותו *ve-ika de-amrei asur be-chamoso*,
and some say בדיעבד *be-di'avad* not. חדא כרבי ישמעאל וחדא כרבי עקיבא
*chada ke-Rabbi Yishmael ve-chada ke-Rabbi Akiva*. One like Rabbi Yishmael and one
like Rabbi Akiva. מאן דאסר כרבי ישמעאל *man de-asar ke-Rabbi Yishmael*, the
one that says even after the wife's death don't marry the mother
is like Rabbi Yishmael דאמר חמותו לאחר מיתה באיסורא קיימא *de-amar chamoso
le-achar misa be-isura kayma*, that remember this debate of Rabbi Yishmael and
Rabbi Akiva whether a man is still gets שריפה *sereifa* if he
marries a woman's mother after his wife's death. So the one that
says like Rabbi Yishmael says it's just the same level of prohibition,
חייב מיתה *chayav misa*, you get שריפה *sereifa*, the whole thing. So
since the prohibition is no different, therefore לגבי גר גזרו ביה רבנן
*legabei ger gazru beih Rabbanan*, the Rabbis did not make a difference
after the wife died because there's no difference in the prohibition even
for a כותי *Kuti*. ומאן דשרי *ve-man de-shari*, the one say that
no, that afterwards we will allow, so then legally it's all מותר
*mutar* anyway because legally they're not related, it's only because it's all
דרבנן *de-rabbanan*. So says כרבי עקיבא דאמר חמותו לאחר מיתה קלש ליה
איסורא *ke-Rabbi Akiva de-amar chamoso le-achar misa kalash leih isura* that says
that even by a Jew the prohibition is weakened. Of course, תוספות
*Tosafos* says weakened still means biblical, still gets כרת *kares*, but okay,
at least it's not a capital crime anymore. ולגבי גר לא גזרו
ביה רבנן *ve-legabei ger lo gazru beih Rabbanan*, so since there's some
degree of weakening and this whole thing is only דרבנן *de-rabbanan*, for
some reason we'll make a difference by the גר *ger* after the
wife died. תוספות *Tosafos* is not exactly sure why just because it's
not במיתה *be-misa* means that we're going to be more lenient, but
okay, and it's all דרבנן *de-rabbanan* anyway for the גר *ger*. All
right, that was the end of that discussion. So we don't know
the answer about whether a גר *ger* can marry his biological brother's
wife, if a wife, so the things that are still really blood
relations we are going to be more מחמיר *machmir* even after conversion,
even though גר שנתגייר כקטן שנולד דמי *ger she-nisgayer ke-katan she-nolad dami*,
as long as the relationship is through the mother. But in terms
of a case about brother's wife, that we're not certain about, the
evidence points that it's מותר *mutar*, at least everybody agrees it's מותר
דאורייתא *mutar de-oraisa*, evidence points it's מותר דרבנן *mutar de-rabbanan*, but the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* did not come to a clear conclusion. Next משנה
Mishna *Mishna*, excuse me, ברוך אתה ה' אלקינו מלך העולם שהכל
נהיה בדברו *Baruch atah Adonai
Eloheinu Melech ha-olam she-hakol nihiyeh bi-devaro*. חמש נשים *Chamesh nashim*, now we're
going to have some fun. חמש נשים שנתערבו ולדותיהן *chamesh nashim she-nisarvu
vildoseihen*,
five women whose children got mixed up. The גמרא Gemara *Gemara* describes
the case that they're in a מחבוא *machavo*, they're all hiding in
a cave, I don't know, from let's say the Romans, okay, and
they're hiding there for a while and they all happen to give
birth at the same time or it's a hospital and then there's
a blackout, we can figure out a scenario. And all of a
sudden all the nameplates got mixed up, nobody actually put on any
you know any name tags or whatever they are, right? And and
now they don't know whose son is whose. Okay? Now, they also,
these five women also happen to have other sons that they all
are, do know whose sons are whose. Okay, so you basically have
a case of, right,
you've got a group here, you've got a group here
of five men, I mean they grow up, and we don't know
whose kids they are, right? And then you've got five others who
are each one of them is a brother to one. Okay, but
you don't know who's whose brother. And then all these people
in
this group get married and wives die without kids. Okay, so now
all the wives need יבום yibum. *yibum* or חליצה chalitzah. *chalitza*, but
you just don't know which is the brother to perform יבום yibum.
*yibum* or חליצה chalitzah *chalitza*. Right, exactly. So let's take a look.
הגדילו התערובות higdilu hata'aruvot. *higdilu ha-ta'arovos*, so these, so the group grew
up, ונשאו נשים *ve-nas'u nashim*, the mixture grew up and they all
married women, ומתו umesu. *u-mesu*, and they all died and didn't leave
over any kids. ארבעה חולצים לאחת ואחת מייבמתה *arba'a choltzim le-achas ve-achas
meyabemesa*. So you go one by one. I mean here are their
counterparts. I really need to get more colors here. Okay, anyway, so
here are their wives.
You see well, they're different color, they've got skirts. Okay, here are
their wives. Okay, so all right,
so basically, for each woman, yeah that's not, oh there, that purple
work? Okay.
I don't know what it is with these things, you leave them
to the people, okay anyway, so each one of these, for every
wife, four people do חליצה chalitzah, *chalitza*,
right, and this guy does, I don't know how to draw, I
just really need color, this guy does יבום yibum. *yibum*. Now why?
How's that going to work? Let's assume you're lucky and this is
the real, he's the
real... Let's say you're not lucky. So one of these guys is
the real brother and did חליצה, chalitzah so you got in the
right חליצה. chalitzah You don't know which one, but you need them
all to do חליצה chalitzah because
because you got to get the right one to do חליצה, chalitzah
then this woman has had חליצה chalitzah done, there's no relationship now,
and he's allowed to marry her. Okay?
That's not יבום.
yibum, That's not יבום. yibum Exactly. We're calling it יבום. yibum. Okay.
So just to give her קידושין kiddushin and whatever it is, right?
Yeah, correct.
Or right, and presumably מאמר ma'amar plus יבום, yibum right, or okay,
exactly plus sex. Okay, fine.
So all of them have to do that.
So then you have to do that with every single woman. Now
you have to do it with every single woman. Now, you could
do it that this guy winds up marrying all five wives. All
or four do חליצה chalitzah of these four do חליצה chalitzah with
every single one and he goes ahead and does יבום yibum with
every one and one of them will be his sister-in-law, the other
will סתם stam be women. But what the משנה's Mishna. going to
say is they all take turns. So for every different wife, a
different four do, well not a different, one of them mixes. So
this is number one. Next group, these four do חליצה chalitzah. and
this one does יבום. yibum Then those, you know, whatever, so that
everybody is doing יבום yibum with one and doing four חליצות. chalitzot.
Why do they take turns? Why, you know, I mean it's just
telling you that that's allowed too, but the גמרא's Gemara. going to
say because maybe you hope there's some סיעתא דשמיא syata d'shmaya and
every single one happens to have done יבום yibum with his sister-in-law.
Or least you're increasing the probability. It's an interesting question, right? I
mean I'm sure you could make a little game theory out of
it. If you have him do יבום yibum with everyone, you definitely
get one יבום yibum out of it. You get to marry to
five wives. If you do this rotation, you could get anywhere between
zero and five יבומים yibumim out of it. Okay, you had a
question, Dov? All right, so let's take a look. Okay, no, let's
just finish the משנה. Mishna ומתו ארבעה חולצין לאחת ואחד מיבם אותה.
Umetu arba'ah chaltzin le'achat ve'echad meyabbem otah.
So that's for the first woman. הוא ושלושה—now Hu ushloshah the one
that did יבום yibum plus three others—חולצין
לאחת—do chaltzin le'achat חליצה chalitzah to the next woman—ואחד מיבם—and ve'echad meyabbem
a different one does יבום yibum. to the next woman. And then
you keep on going around the circle. נמצאו ארבע חליצות ויבום לכל
אחת ואחת. Nimtze'u arba chalitzot veyibum lechol achat ve'achat. Every woman gets
four חליצות chalitzot and one יבום yibum and we do it at
least the way the משנה's Mishna. described, each woman gets a different
man doing יבום yibum with her. So the גמרא Gemara says, ודוקא
מחלץ והדר ייבומי. Vedavka machlatz vehadar yibumei. Let's first of all be
clear, first she receives חליצה chalitzah. from the four men and then
יבום. yibum אבל ייבומי ברישא לא, Aval yibumei bereisha lo,
but you can't start with doing יבום yibum obviously, דקפגע ביבמה לשוק.
dekaphaga bivevamah lashuk.
This woman might not be his sister-in-law and then she still requires
חליצה chalitzah and he's having sex with a woman who needs חליצה.
chalitzah, Now, מאי הוא ושלושה חולצין לאחת? Mai hu ushloshah chaltzin le'achat?
Why do you go ahead and have him and three do the
next woman? Why does a different one do יבום yibum. on the
next woman? דלא תימא לייבם חד לכולהו. Dela teima leyabbem chad lechulhu.
אלא כל חד וחד מייבם חד. Ela kol chad vechad meyabbem chad.
So we don't want one to do יבום yibum. with all, we
want a different one to do יבום yibum with each woman. דילמא
מסטרמיא לדידיה. Dilma mistarmia l'didei.
Maybe each one, there'll be a little סיעתא דשמיא, syata d'shmaya, we'll
get his sister-in-law and each one will perform יבום. yibum Dov asked
a question, wanted to know something?
He says, I mean, I know you shouldn't answer this, but like,
what about an אבילות aveilus quest—like what do they do about the
אבילות? aveilus?
Ah, well we'll talk a little bit about that in the גמרא.
Gemara Yeah, in the next משנה.
Yeah, but just an observation that
this is a kind of a different approach, it seems to me.
The previous משניות mishnayot talked about missing persons and the woman always,
you know, suffered in
a way, right?
And here, we're taking steps to, you know, like you could say
everybody does חליצה chalitzah. and you don't have to worry about all
this. Right? But then the woman doesn't get doesn't get married.
Right, presumably to do יבום.
yibum Right, assuming, right,
assuming that the יבום yibum. is something that the woman wants, right,
to
make sure that she gets, you know, not her fault, and anyway,
right.
It's a good point. We are sort of making sure she gets
a יבום yibum. out of this and not just saying oh everybody
does חליצה. chalitzah, That is correct. Again, I don't know if the
גמרא's Gemara concern is the woman or the גמרא's Gemara concern like
that the מצוה mitzvah יבום yibum gets done, you know, in general,
but it's true.
But
it's just trying to have fun, exactly.
Okay, exactly. Dov has a language question. מסטרמיא לדידיה Mistarmia l'didei means
סיעתא דשמיא? syata d'shmaya?
No, I threw in סיעתא דשמיא, syata d'shmaya, but מסטרמיא—I mistarmia mean
you could say it means chance.
מסטרמיא לדידיה, Mistarmia l'didei, like his right one gets thrown to him,
his right one by, you know, happens to fall in to fall
in his lot. Okay. מקצתן אחין ומקצתן שאין אחין. Miktzatan achin umiktzatan
she'ein achin. Now,
let's say האחין חולצין ושאין אחין מיבמין. ha'achin chaltzin veshe'ein achin meyabbemin.
So
if some are brothers and some aren't, so the brothers do חליצה
chalitzah and the non-brothers do יבום. yibum, Now that seems to be
completely nonsensical. So מאי קאמר, mai ka'amar, what are you saying? הכי
קאמר, hachi ka'amar, אמר רב ספרא, Amar Rav Safra, this is what
it means. מקצת אחין מן האב ומקצת אחין מן האם. Miktzat achin
min ha'av umiktzat achin min ha'em. If some of them are paternal
brothers and some are maternal brothers, אחין מן האם חולצין ואחין מן
האב מיבמין. achin min ha'em chaltzin ve'achin min ha'av meyabbemin. The maternal
brothers do חליצה, chalitzah. the paternal ones do יבום. yibum? Now that
also doesn't make sense, because if if some of these guys are
only are only maternal brothers to some of these, then they don't
do יבום yibum. or חליצה. chalitzah. Maternal brother is out of the
picture, right, unrelated. So רש"י Rashi explains... explains what it means, and
I won't walk you through to figure out how this works, that
the case is that let's say some of these guys, right, let's
say this guy here is a paternal brother to one of them,
and a maternal brother to another, okay. We don't know who. But
he's got both a maternal brother in the mix and a paternal
brother in the mix. So if that's true, he's not allowed to
do ייבום. yibbum. He's got to do חליצה, chalitzah 'cause one of
these guys is his paternal brother. Right, and so one of these
women is his paternal brother's wife, so he's got to do חליצה
chalitzah to all the women, right, 'cause he's got to free his
paternal brother's wife. So he still has to do חליצה. chalitzah, Why
can he not do ייבום? yibbum? Because he might do ייבום yibbum
with his maternal brother's wife, which is an איסור עריות issur arayos
and no מצוה mitzvah of חליצה. chalitzah. Okay? So because he's got
a paternal brother in the mix, he's got to do חליצה chalitzah,
with all, he's got to do חליצה chalitzah. with all the women
to free his maternal brother's, his paternal brother's wife. Because he's got
a maternal brother in the mix, he can't do ייבום yibbum 'cause
then there would be an איסור עריות. issur arayos. Okay?
So what do you do over the total in terms of inheritance?
Alright, we'll worry about that later. Yeah, yeah, let's not talk about
that now. We'll get to something like that later. מקצתן כהנים ומקצתן
שאין כהנים. miktzasam kohanim umiktzasam she'ein kohanim.
Some of them are כהנים kohanim and some are not. So a
כהן kohen cannot go ahead and do ייבום yibbum with a woman
who had חליצה, chalitzah, but no ייבום yibbum can be done here
until חליצות chalitzos are done. Right? Because any woman you might not
be your sister-in-law might require חליצה. chalitzah So in that case, כהנים
חולצין שאין כהנים מיבמין. kohanim chaltzin she'ein kohanim meyabmim. The כהנים kohanim
can only do חליצה, chalitzah the non-כהנים kohanim can do ייבום, yibbum,
and in that case you might have a man doing ייבום yibbum
with more than one woman, because, you know, for the כהן kohen
you don't have the equal matching of men doing ייבום yibbum to
women who need ייבום yibbum or חליצה. chalitzah מקצתן כהנים ומקצתן אחין
מן האם. miktzasam kohanim umiktzasam achin min ha-eim.
So let's say you've got some of them that's got some maternal
brothers in the mix. They also have paternal but they also have
maternal. And you have some of them who are כהנים kohanim and
nobody who is not, who's both a non-כהן kohen and has no
maternal brother. So nobody here can do ייבום, yibbum, right? The people
with maternal brothers can't do ייבום, yibbum, they might have a sister-in-law
who was without a מצוה mitzvah of ייבום yibbum in there, and
the כהנים kohanim can't do it because they, because the woman might
be a חלוצה. chalutzah.
So in that case, אלו ואלו
חולצין ולא מיבמין,
elu
va-elu
chaltzin velo miyavmim,
everybody does חליצה, chalitzah no ייבום yibbum gets done. תנו רבנן, tanu
rabanan, דף צ״ט עמוד א׳. daf tzadi tes amud aleph. יש חולץ
לאמו מספק לאחותו מספק לבתו מספק. yesh choletz le-imo misafek la-achoso misafek
levito misafek.
There will be a case that somebody might have to wind up
doing חליצה chalitzah to a woman, to his mother because of a
doubt, or to his sister because of a doubt, or to his
daughter because of a doubt. כיצד, keitzad, what's the case? אמו ואשה
אחרת. imo ve-ishah acheres. You have his mother and another woman. ולהן
שני זכרים. velahen shenei zecharim. And they have two male sons. וחזרו
וילדו שני זכרים במערה. ve-chazru ve-yaldu shenei zecharim be-mecharah.
And then they've, then his mother and another woman have two sons
in a cave and you don't know who's whose. ובא בנה של
זו ונשא אמה של זו. uva benah shel zo ve-nasa imah shel
zo.
Okay, so basically,
here you've got his mother and another woman, okay.
They each have some sons who they don't know who's whose, and
they each have a son that's, you know, who they know who's
whose, okay. And comes along this guy
and marries, wait a second, hold on, let me just double check
this. ובא, right, ובא ובא ובא בנה של
זו ונשא אמה של
זו,
ve-nasa
imah shel zo, right.
Okay, so this guy comes and marries this woman, this guy's mother,
okay. This guy marries the mother, and then what happens? Wait, and
he marries the mother? Hold on.
I know, I
know, hold on, hold on.
This is actually a possible
case of
incest. Not yet.
A minute.
But it will be, right? Yeah, that's what we're, that's what we're
searching for.
Oh,
okay, fine fine fine. He marries his mother, okay. And then, I
mean he marries, whatever. This guy marries this guy and then this
guy marries this guy's mother, but that doesn't, we're not going to
complicate it, okay? And then he dies. All right? He dies. So
the mother needs ייבום. yibbum. Okay, this woman needs ייבום. yibbum. Who
has to do ייבום? yibbum? His brother, right? His brother's one of
these guys. One of these guys has to do ייבום yibbum or
חליצה chalitzah to the mother. Problem is that one of them has
to do ייבום yibbum or חליצה chalitzah and the other guy, it's
his mother. Right? So they both do, nobody can do ייבום yibbum
with her because she's his mother. They both do חליצה chalitzah to
that woman, so you now a person is doing חליצה chalitzah to
a woman who might be his mother. One of them is definitely
doing חליצה chalitzah to a woman who's his mother. Okay? Exactly. So,
okay, ונשא אמה של זו, בנה של זו נשא אמה של זו,
benah shel zo nasa imah shel zo,
you don't really need the parallel case, ומתו. no boys, זה חולץ
לשתיהם וזה חולץ לשתיהם. zeh choletz l'shteihem v'zeh choletz l'shteihem.
So again, if it's each, you know, if it's happened in parallel,
both one, both of these guys are doing חליצה chalitzah to both
women. Okay, so נמצא כל אחד ואחד חולץ לאמו מספק. nimtza kol
echad v'echad choletz l'imo misafek. Everybody is definitely is doing, so if
it were just one way, so then it would also be true
that each one, no, then only one of them is doing חליצה
chalitzah to his mother מספק. misafek. Okay, one is doing חליצה chalitzah
to his sister-in-law and the other is doing חליצה chalitzah to his
mother מספק. misafek. If it's both ways, then both of them are
doing חליצה chalitzah to their mothers מספק. misafek.
But fine, you get a guy doing חליצה chalitzah to his mother
מספק. misafek. Okay, ואחותו מספק כיצד? v'achoto misafek keitzad?
What's the case about a sister?
אמו ואישה אחרת שילדו שתי נקבות במחבא.
imo v'isha
acheret she'yaldu shtei nekeivot b'machba.
Okay,
his mother and another woman had two, had two daughters. ובאו אחיהם
שלא מאותה האם ונשאום. u'vau acheihem shelo m'ota ha'em v'nasau'um.
And then their half-brothers came and married them.
ומתו בלא בנים. u'metu belo banim. So, what happened again?
Again, all this made sense last night. Okay, let's see if we've
got it. Okay.
So, they had these two daughters
in
the cave, okay, and we don't know who's who. And then they've
got
these
sons. And who, who came and married them? אחיהם שלא מן האם.
acheihem shelo min ha'em. Oh, so now here you've got his, got
it. Okay, they have the same father and a different mother. Okay,
and here he's got a different mother, right? Okay, so he can
marry one of these women, because one of these women, right, is
not, is not related to him. Different father, different mother. Everybody, is
that clear? Right, these guys share a father, not a mother. So
he goes ahead and marries one of them and then, and then,
okay, fine, and then the same with the guy on the other
side, okay? But we won't worry about the other side. And then
what happens? ובאו אחיהם שלא מאותה האם ונשאום ומתו בלא בנים.
u'vau acheihem shelo m'ota ha'em
v'nasau'um u'metu belo banim. So
and then these guys die.
How are those two guys related? These two?
These two, they're paternal brothers.
Their paternal, they have the same father.
Father, yeah. Okay, they've got the same father, different mother. So then
this, so then he dies. So then then this guy here, who's
the paternal brother, has got to do חליצה chalitzah to his brother's,
to his brother's wife. But his brother's wife might be his sister.
And he's got to do חליצה chalitzah to, right,
so he can't do יבום, yibum he's got to do חליצה chalitzah
to both.
Right, now actually in that case, this guy is only married to
one woman. So he's got to do, ah, but then the same
thing happened here, right? And so and he knows, wait a minute,
only wait, he knows which woman he's doing חליצה chalitzah to?
He's got to do חליצה chalitzah to both because he doesn't know
which one is his sister and which one is,
yeah, but this guy is only married to one woman, so
only one of them is the widow now.
Yeah, then the same thing happened on the other one and the
other guy died. But that's okay, but that's okay, but the point
is he's doing חליצה chalitzah to a woman who is his ספק
safek sister. It's a little different than in the other case. Rashi
tries to make it more similar. It's not like he's definitely doing
חליצה chalitzah to his sister out of doubt, he's doing חליצה chalitzah,
to a woman who might be his sister. Right. Okay, fine, we'll
just leave it at that for now. We could make it a
more parallel case and Rashi figures it out, but I'm not going
to worry about it. Okay, חולץ לשתיהם. choletz l'shteihem. So, ובאו אחיהם
שלא מאותה האם ונשאום. u'vau acheihem shelo m'ota ha'em v'nasau'um. Oh,
because what Rashi has is, I think the case was, because it
says שתיהם. shteihem. Here's the case. There are two brothers.
Two paternal brothers. Here's the case, okay? Forget this thing on the
other... two paternal brothers, okay? So they both married. So now he
has two חליצות chalitzot to do, right? Because both of his, both
of these women were married to his brother. One of them, however,
is his sister. Okay, so he's going to do חליצה chalitzah to
both of them and he's definitely doing חליצה chalitzah. to his sister
מספק. misafek. All right.
Okay, ומתו בלא בנים חולץ לשתיהם נמצא חולץ אחותו מספק. u'metu belo
banim choletz l'shteihem nimtza choletz achoto misafek. ובתו מספק כיצד? u'vito misafek
keitzad?
What's the case about his daughter? אישה ואישה אחרת שילדו שתי נקבות
במחבא. isha v'isha acheret she'yaldu shtei nekeivot b'machba.
His wife and another woman had two daughters. ובאו
אחיהם ונשאום ומתו בלא בנים. u'vau acheihem v'nasau'um u'metu belo banim. And
then their brothers came and married them. This
guy's brother. Okay, here. He,
he and his wife
had
a daughter, right? And then this other woman had a daughter and
they've had these daughters here that they don't know who's who.
Okay, then comes along his brother. His brother's allowed to marry his
niece, right? No restrictions. And his brother marries, right? And let's say
we've got another brother also just for the fun of it that
also marries.
They don't have to worry about it, they're allowed to marry their
niece. And then they both die. One of these
is his wife, one of them is his brother's wife, one of
them is his brother's wife who's his daughter. He doesn't know who's
who, he does חליצה chalitzah to both of them, even though he's
doing חליצה, chalitzah. one of them he's doing חליצה chalitzah. to is
his daughter. Okay?
All right. ובסיפא ובבנים uv'sefa uv'banim ואי בעית אימא v'i ba'is eima
ואחיהם הנשואים v'achaiham hanesuim ובסיפא ובבנים uv'sefa uv'banim זה חולץ לביתו מספק
zeh choletz l'bito mi'safek וזה חולץ לביתו מספק. v'zeh choletz l'bito mi'safek.
Okay? And then you,
whatever, the גמרא Gemara has it, I get it, two brothers on
the same side, could be brothers on opposite sides, same difference, whatever.
Moving on. All right. תניא, Tanya, we've learned in a ברייתא. Braisa.
היה רבי מאיר אומר, haya Rebbi Meir omer, איש ואישה, ish v'isha,
sometimes שמהולידין shemolidin it's worth having fun with these scenarios. Another case.
פעמים שמהולידין חמש אומות. pe'amim shemolidin chamesh umot.
Sometimes a man and a woman could have five children which are
of five different nations, now not literally nationalities, but הלכתי halachic categories.
כיצד? keitzad? ישראל שלקח עבד ושפחה מן השוק. Yisrael she'lakach eved v'shifcha
min hashuk. A Jew bought a non-Jewish male and female slave from
the marketplace. ולהם שני בנים, v'lahem shenei vanim, and they had two
biological children. Now, the הלכה, halacha, these biological children are not slaves.
עבד ושפחה eved v'shifcha who are married to each other?
Yeah, okay. And they're not and the biological children are not slaves.
Okay, ונתגייר. v'nitgayair. Now because רש"י Rashi discusses it might be that
the assumption is that slaves owned by non-Jews, their children are not
considered to be slaves of the owner. Okay. So, but anyway, you
can have another scenario also that they were taken as slaves after
they had had the children. Okay, so they already have two children.
Now, ונתגייר. v'nitgayair. Now those two children that they had had, converted.
ונתגייר אחד מהם. v'nitgayair echad mehem. I'm sorry, one of them converted.
So already you're starting with these two parents that have two kids,
one is Jewish and one is not. נמצא אחד גר ואחד עובד
כוכבים. nimtza echad geir v'echad oved kochavim. You got it? You have
two parents, one of their kids converted, one's Jewish, one's not, the
two parents however are slaves. Okay. Now, הטבילו לשם עבדות. hitbilu l'shem
avdus. Now, these two parents you took as slaves and you put
them in the מקווה mikvah to be עבד כנעני. eved Kna'ani. ונזקק
זה לזה. v'nizkak zeh la'zeh. And then they had sex. הרי כאן,
harei kan, and then they had a kid. So now they're your
הלכתי halachic slave, their kid is a slave. הרי כאן גר ועובד
כוכבים ועבד. harei kan geir v'oved kochavim v'eved. Now they've got three
kids. They've got their free non-Jew, free Jew who they had before
they were taken as slaves by you the Jew, and now they've
got a child who's a slave. שיחרר את השפחה. shichrar es hashifcha.
Now you freed the mother. ובא עליה העבד. u'ba aleha ha'eved. And
the slave continued to have sex with her. הרי כאן גר ועובד
כוכבים ועבד וממזר. harei kan geir v'oved kochavim v'eved u'mamzer. Now the
next kid is a ממזר, mamzer, this is following the position of
רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva right that a עבד eved and a and
a free woman, the child is a
ממזר. mamzer. Okay. So I mean רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, this is
is it רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva
or רבי מאיר? Rebbi Meir? Let's take a look. I'm trying to
remember. רש"י Rashi says it. Who was it?
There's a note you want me to read it? Yeah, what's it
say? הלשון halashon says רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir defines a ממזר mamzer
as the child
of a man and woman...
yeah,
רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, right. רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, I thought it
was רבי מאיר, Rebbi Meir, right. Okay. Okay now שיחרר שניהם. shichrar
shenehem.
Yeah, fine. שיחרר שניהם. shichrar shenehem. רבי עקיבא Rebbi Akiva also has
a broader ממזר mamzer category. But this is specifically about the whole
idea of an עבד eved and a free woman. Okay, so now
you got four, okay?
Jew, non-Jew, slave, ממזר. mamzer. שיחרר שניהם והשיאם זה לזה. shichrar shenehem
v'hisiam zeh la'zeh.
Now you freed the two of them and they now they and
then they married them to one another. הרי כאן הוא אחד גר
ועובד כוכבים ועבד וממזר וישראל. harei kan hu echad geir v'oved kochavim
v'eved u'mamzer v'Yisrael.
So now you have a convert, right? 'Cause I've been saying Jew
but it's really been convert. You have a you started with a
convert, non-Jew, slave, ממזר, mamzer, and now you have a naturally born
Jew. Okay, so that was all very fun. But מאי קמשמע לן,
mai kamashma lan, what's the חידוש chiddush with any of that? So
the גמרא Gemara says עובד כוכבים ועבד הבא על בת ישראל הוי
ממזר. oved kochavim v'eved haba al bas Yisrael havei mamzer. The חידוש
chiddush is for ממזר mamzer case, that since it was a slave
with a free woman, the child is considered a ממזר, mamzer, at
least according to this ברייתא. Baraisa תנו רבנן, tanu rabanan, יש מוכר
את אביו להגבות את כתובת אמו. yesh mocher es aviv lehagbot es
kesuvas immo. A man can wind up selling his father in order
to pay off his mother's כתובה. kesuva. כיצד? keitzad? You can tell
the גמרא Gemara. is having fun yesterday or the day... Friday today.
כיצד? keitzad? ישראל שלקח עבד ושפחה מן השוק. Yisrael she'lakach eved v'shifcha
min hashuk. A Jew bought a male and female slave from the
marketplace. ולהם בן, v'lahem ben, and they had a child. ושיחרר את
השפחה, v'shichrar es hashifcha, and he freed the slave, ונשאה, u'nesa'ah,
and he married her. So now basically he's married to this woman
and he owns this woman's ex-husband, right, as a slave. All
right. Okay, ואמר וכתב כל נכסי לבני. v'amar v'chasav kol nechasai l'vni.
And then after he married this woman, he transferred all of his
property to her son.
Okay. To this non-Jewish boy potentially.
Yeah to this slave son, okay? Now,
and then what happens? He dies. So now his mother, his biological
mother, now a free woman, wants to collect her ketubah. Who owns
all of the property? Where does she have a lien on the
property? Her biological son, right, owns the property. And one of the
things that her biological son owns is his biological father, okay? So
in order to pay off his mother's ketubah, he sells his father.
Okay. נמצא זה מוכר את אביו להגבות לאמו כתובתה. Nimtza Zeh Mochar
Et Aviv Lehagevot Le'imo Ketuvatah. What? The slave?
Well, he's quasi-Jewish.
He's an עבד כנעני. Eved Kna'ani. He's not just quasi-Jewish slave.
So you solve the problem by just having him be freed too.
Yeah, I mean, if you want to make him Jewish, have him
freed as well. Okay.
But it's like a little bit problematic for today.
I don't know. מה קמשמע לן? Ma Kamashma Lan? What does it
teach us? כולה רבי מאיר היא. Kula Rabbi Meir Hi. It's telling
you like Rabbi Meir. ואעבדא כמטלטלי Ve'avda Kemetalteli because we said the
first point about עובדי כוכבים Ovdei Kochavim was also, you know, that
the child was a ממזר mamzer was Rabbi Meir. ואעבדא כמטלטלי ומטלטלי
משתעבדי לכתובה. Ve'avda Kemetalteli Umetalteli Mishta'abdi Liketuvah. So one of the, the
one חידוש chiddush is that even though a slave is considered chattel,
which is funny, when is a slave considered real estate, when is
it chattel, but even if you consider it chattel, it works like
Rabbi Meir who says that chattel has an, is, is encumbered, there
can be a lien on chattel to pay off a כתובה. ketubah.
So that's the whole point of the חידוש, chiddush, not to tell
you that you can sell off your father. ואי בעית אימא קמשמע
לן עבדא כמקרקעי דמי. Ve'ee Ba'it Teima Kamashma Lan Avda Kemikarkei Dami.
Or it's telling you it's not because he's chattel, but the reason
it works is because he, because he is considered like real estate
and there's a lien on real estate and there's a lien on
עבדים. avadim. So it's really not telling you anything about selling off
your father, it's just telling you a הלכה halacha about whether slaves
have a lien on them to pay off כתובה. ketubah. All right.
Moving on. האשה שנתערב ולדה בולד כלתה. Ha'isha Shenitarve Valdah Bevlad Kaltah.
A woman whose child gets mixed up with her daughter-in-law's child, okay?
So basically you've got a man and his nephew, right? Is that
clear? Okay.
Here they are. They have a nice boy, okay?
And he's married to this woman.
What happened? My orange became red now because it got mixed up
with... Okay, anyway, they have this nice
woman
and and so they and they have a child.
Who's your daughter-in-law over there?
He marries, yeah, I don't know why I'm doing this as a
dotted line. Anyway, so they've got a they've got a kid. And
she's got a kid, right?
Also a kid here. And these get mixed up and you don't
know whose is whose. All right? So somebody is, you don't know
whether who is the uncle and who is the nephew. All right?
Is that clear? Yes? Sort of? Okay, you don't know who's the
uncle and who's the nephew.
He's his own grandpa, right? So anyway, הגדילו התערובות ונשאו נשים. Higdilu
Hata'arovot Venase'u Nashim.
So they grew up, they married women. ומתו בני הכלה ומתו. Umetu
Bnei Hakallah Umetu. And they died. בני הכלה חולצין ולא מייבמין. Bnei
Hakallah Choltzin Velo Meyabmin.
So
the other brothers here, what are they going to do to the,
what's this guy going to do to the wife?
So can he
do יבום? yibum? Well, if he gets the right woman, he's doing
יבום. yibum If he gets the wrong woman, who is the wrong
woman? The wrong woman is his uncle's wife, his aunt. So that's
an עריות. arayot. So he's not able to do יבום with either
because one of them might be his aunt. So he has to
do חליצה. chalitza So בני הכלה חולצין ולא מייבמין שספק אשת אחיו
ספק אשת אחי אביו. Bnei Hakallah Choltzin Velo Meyabmin She'safek Eshet Achiv
Safek Eshet Achie Aviv.
It might be his brother's wife, it might be his uncle's, uncle's
wife. בני הזקנה, Bnei Hazekenah, now if,
now they've got other kids, okay, or maybe even him if he's
a brother, okay, whatever, anyway, they've got other kids. So can he
do יבום? Well, sure, because either it's his brother's wife or it's
his niece, right? His nephew's wife. That's okay. בני הזקנה או חולצין
או מייבמין שספק אשת אחיו ואשת בן אחיו.
Bnei Hazekenah O Choltzin O
Meyabmin She'safek Eshet Achiv Ve'eshet Ben Achiv. Either it's his brother's wife
or his nephew's wife. מתו הכשרים. Metu Hakesherim. If the kosher ones
die.
Now
the גמרא Gemara says it's not like the others are פסול, pasul,
but the וודאיים. vadayim. Okay, these guys now are the ones who
die.
And these guys have to do חליצה chalitza with their wives left
behind. So then it just flips, okay? So you'll see. התערובת לבני
הזקנה חולצין ולא מייבמין. Hata'arovot Livnei Hazekenah Choltzin Velo Meyabmin.
So this guy's wife can only get חליצה. chalitza Why? Because for
one of them it will be the brother's wife, but the other
one will be the aunt. So they, so when
vis-a-vis his wife they can only do חליצה. chalitza. שספק אשת
אחיו ואשת אחי אביו. She'safek Eshet Achiv Ve'eshet Achie Aviv. For one
of them it's a brother's wife and for one of them... Uncle's
wife. לבני הכלה, Livnei Hakalah, when it comes to this guy's wife
then you're good, one can do יבום because for one of them
it's a brother's wife and for the other it's a nephew's, nephew's
wife which is okay. So לבני הכלה Livnei Hakalah אחד חולץ ואחד
מייבם. echad choletz ve'echad meyabem. Okay, now כוהנת שנתערב ולדה בולד שפחתה.
Kohenet shenitarav valdah b'valad shifchatah.
You have a כוהן's Kohen wife whose child gets mixed up with
her servant's, her slave's child. Okay, so one of them is a
כוהן Kohen and the other is a slave. But the interesting thing
is the slave of a כוהן Kohen eats תרומה. trumah. So הרי
אלו אוכלים בתרומה. harei elu ochlim b'trumah. They can eat תרומה trumah
because either way one of them is a כוהן, Kohen, וחולקין חלק
אחד בגורן. vecholkin chelek echad bagoren.
They can get one portion in the גורן goren because you know
a slave gets his master's portion so you know together they're only
entitled to one portion.
ואינם מטמאים למתים. ve'einam mitam'im lemetim. In other words they can't become
טמא tamei to a מת mes because one of them's a כוהן.
Kohen. ואינם נושאים נשים. ve'einam nosim nashim. And they can't get married
because one of them a כוהן Kohen can only marry a free
woman and one's a slave, alright we'll get to there.
בין כשירות בין פסולות. bein k'sherot bein psulot.
They can't marry whether כשירה k'sherot women or not כשירה k'sherot women
because whatever the you know
they're mutually exclusive groups of the women they can marry. הגדילו התערובות.
They grew up. ושחררו זה את זה. veshichreru zeh et zeh. And
they freed one another. Meaning they said if you're the slave and
I'm the master I'm freeing you and the other said the same.
Okay.
Now they're both free people but one's a כוהן Kohen and one
is a freed slave. So in this case נושאים נשים. nosim nashim.
They can get married, ראויות לכהונה. re'uyot l'khunah. As long as the
women are women who are permitted to marry כוהנים. kohanim. Okay, so
you can't marry a גרושה וחלוצה grushah vechalutzah and so on but
fine. ואינם מטמאים למתים. ve'einam mitam'im lemetim. Can't be טמא tamei because
again one of them is still a כוהן. Kohen. ואם נטמאו אינם
סופגים את הארבעים. ve'im nitm'u einam sofgin et ha'arbaim. If they did
they don't get lashes because because you don't know who's the ודאי
vadai כוהן Kohen is.
ואינם אוכלים בתרומה. ve'einam ochlim b'trumah.
They can't eat תרומה trumah because one of them is no longer
a slave so if you were a freed slave you can't eat
תרומה. trumah. ואם אכלו אינם משלמים קרן וחומש. ve'im achlu einam meshalmim
keren v'chomesh. If they did eat they don't have to pay the
קרן keren and the חומש chomesh because you might be a כוהן
Kohen eating your own תרומה. trumah. ואינם חולקים על הגורן. ve'einam cholkim
al hagoren. And they can't get the תרומה trumah at on the
threshing floor because one of them isn't a כוהן Kohen or the
slave of a כוהן. Kohen. ומוכרין את התרומה.
umochrin
et hatrumah.
Now their own תרומה trumahs that they're מפריש mafrish they don't have
to give it to a כוהן Kohen because because they can say
המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah. They might be a
כוהן Kohen and prove that it's yours. On the other hand they
can't eat it because they might not be a כוהן. Kohen. So
what do they do with this תרומה trumah that they own that
they can't eat? So they sell it והדמים שלהן vehadamim shelahen and
they can keep the money. ואינם חולקים בקדשי המקדש. ve'einam cholkim b'kodshei
hamikdash.
They don't get a portion in the קדשים kodshim in the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. You know even if you're not a כוהן Kohen
you get a portion or whatever of the עורות orot etc. You
don't get a portion because maybe you're not a כוהן. Kohen. ואין
נותנים להם קדשים. ve'ein notnim lahem kodshim. You don't give them קרבנות
korbanot to be מקריב makriv obviously because they can't be מקריב makriv
קרבנות korbanot and it might also mean you don't give them a
בכור bechor as we'll see. ואין מוציאין שלהם מידם. ve'ein motzi'in shelahem
miyadam. And you don't take their קרבנות korbanot out of their hand.
Now what exactly that means is unclear because does it mean that
they can be מקריב makriv their own קרבן? korban? They're not allowed
to be מקריב makriv you don't know which one is the כוהן.
Kohen. So רש"י Rashi big discussion רש"י תוספות Rashi Tosfos but בקיצור
bekitzur what it means is is that either if they have a
בכור bechor you know if they themselves their animal has a בכור
bechor they don't have to give it to another כוהן Kohen because
they can say maybe I'm the כוהן. Kohen. Now they can't go
ahead and be מקריב makriv it but they can wait until it
gets a מום. mum. And once a בכור bechor has a מום
mum the כוהן Kohen can eat it without being מקריב. makriv. It
can eat it outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. That's the simple
scenario. The other possibility רש"י Rashi says is if they have a
קרבן korban to bring like an עולה או חטאת. olah o chatat.
So if they you knew they were a כוהן Kohen they could
say I'm bringing it myself and I'm entitled therefore to you know
the portion of it etc. If they don't know since you don't
know they're a כוהן Kohen they can still say stipulate and say
I'm going to designate the כוהן Kohen that's going to bring it
for me and I'm going to keep sort of you know the
עור or or whatever because it might be I might be entitled
to it it might be mine but he can't actually do the
עבודה avodah and he can't eat the stuff that's קדשים. kodshim. Right.
Anyway fine. Okay. Now it says but בכור bechor is the easier
scenario. ופטורים מן הזרוע ומן הלחיים ומן הקיבה. u'pturim min hazroa u'min
halechayayim u'min hakeivah. They don't have to give the portions when you
שוחט shecht an animal the meat that goes to a כוהן Kohen
because that's not קדשים kodshim and they might be a כוהן Kohen
so they get to keep so it's המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi
mechavero alav hara'ayah. ובכורו. uvchoro.
And back to the בכור. bechor.
They cannot eat that?
Yes they can. It's not קדשים kodshim it's just ממונות mamonot belongs
to the כוהן. Kohen. ובכורו ירעה עד שיסתאב. uvchoro yireh ad sheyista'ev.
And if they have a בכור bechor you let it graze until
it gets a מום. mum. Right. They can't bring it because they
might not be a כוהן Kohen and they couldn't eat it if
it was brought as a קרבן. korban. But if they are doing
if they're waiting for it to get a מום mum then you
wait then they can eat it and bring it outside the בית
המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. ונותנין עליו חומרי כוהנים וחומרי ישראלים. venotnim alav chomrei
kohanim v'chomrei yisraelim.
And you treat him with the stringencies of כוהנים kohanim and ישראלים.
yisraelim. Okay.
Right. And that will be explained as we've sort of been saying
that anyway. Okay. Now it says like this גמרא. Gemara מתו
הכשרים. meisu hakesherim. So in the case about all of this when
it says the kosher ones died, or that was actually the one
about whatever, anyway so it says אטו אלא הנך משום דאיערמי הוו
הוו פסולין ela hanach mishum deierami havu havu psulin
the ones that you're confused about are פסול? pasul? So אמר רב
פפא amar Rav Pappa אימא ומתו הודאים. eima umisu havadayim. It doesn't
mean kosher, it means the ones we know who what we're talking
about, the ודאים. vadayim. Okay, לבני הכלה אחד חולץ וכולי livnei hakala
echad choletz vechu etc. ודווקא vedavka and so then you know and
then it talks about with which one they you know they do
you know one does חליצה one does ייבום yibum in one of
those scenarios. ודווקא ברישא חליצה והדר ייבום, vedavka breisha chalitza vehadar yibum,
again pointing out what I said before, that have to be the
order: first חליצה then ייבום, yibum, אבל ייבום ברישא לא aval yibum
breisha lo even in these scenarios you can't do ייבום yibum first,
דקפגע ביבמה לשוק dekapaga biyvama lashuk 'cause he obviously you might get
the order wrong and she might be have to get חליצה and
then it will be sex with a woman who's awaiting חליצה. Okay,
כוהנת שנתערבה. kohenes shenisarva. Now so the first case is where a
son when we diagrammed it but the גמרא Gemara doesn't have much
to say about it, we get to the case of the כוהן
kohen which is a new case. חלק אחד? chelek echad? Of course
they they get only one portion, the כוהן kohen this this guy
one of them who was a כוהן kohen and one of whom
is an עבד eved and you don't know who's who. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, אימא חלק כאחד. eima chelek ke'echad. No, it
means that when they go to collect the תרומה terumah they have
to go together. What does that mean? תנן tnan כמאן דאמר אין
חולקין תרומה לעבד אלא אם כן רבו עמו keman deamar ein cholkin
terumah leeved ela im kein rabo imo like the person that says
that you do not give תרומה terumah in the threshing floor to
the slave unless the master is there, even if you know that
you're only going to give once to that family, you will not
deliver it to the עבד eved even if you have no questions
that they're not going to go for double-dipping, you don't deliver to
the עבד eved without the master there. Why not? So that's what
it means אחד, echad, it means that they're coming together. Why not?
דתניא detanya we learned in a ברייתא Baraisa אין חולקין תרומה לעבד
אלא אם כן רבו עמו דברי רבי יהודה. ein cholkin terumah leeved
ela im kein rabo imo divrei Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says you only do it the slave together with the master. רבי
יוסי אומר יכול שיאמר, Rabbi Yossi omer yachol sheyomar, שיאמר, sheyomar, so
no, in this case he could say אם כהן אני תנו לי
בשביל עצמי, im kohen ani tnu li bishvil atzmi, if I'm a
כוהן kohen give me on my own accord, ואם עבד לכהן אני
תנו לי בשביל רבי, ve'im eved lekohen ani tnu li bishvil rabi,
and if I'm a slave give me for my rebbe. So it's
not clear why you say according to the first opinion says that
they have to go together. So the גמרא Gemara is now going
to explain it out. במקומו של רבי יהודה היו מעלין מתרומה ליוחסין.
bimkomo shel Rabbi Yehuda hayu maalin miterumah leyuchsin. In רבי יהודה's Rabbi
Yehuda place, if they would say that if somebody collected תרומה, terumah,
they would assume he was a כוהן kohen and therefore they would
marry him off to a women who are appropriate for כוהנים. kohanim.
So in that's true, if the perception is, if people have the
assumption that anybody who gets תרומה's terumah a כוהן, kohen, then you
can't send your עבד eved to collect תרומה terumah 'cause people will
think he's a כוהן. kohen. Okay? So therefore you so therefore in
those scenarios you can only send it's obviously a little bit of
circular: which comes first? Because only כוהנים kohanim are collecting תרומה, terumah,
people perceive it that you only give כוהנים kohanim תרומה terumah and
therefore you're only allowed to give כוהנים kohanim תרומה, terumah, right? If
the reality started the other way that people would send their עבדים
avadim to collect תרומה, terumah, people would understand that people who collect
תרומה terumah are not necessarily כוהנים kohanim and then they wouldn't, you
know and then you'd be allowed to send your you know your
עבד eved to collect תרומה. terumah. So sort of like the reality
creates expectation creates the הלכה. halacha. It's all served I understand but
I'm saying it's all like it's a chicken and an egg, it's
a chicken and an egg. Okay, so anyway, okay, דברי רבי יהודה.
divrei Rabbi Yehuda. רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi Yossi omer fine, תנו לי
בשביל רבי. tnu li bishvil rabi. במקומו של רבי יהודה היו מעלין
מתרומה ליוחסין. bimkomo shel Rabbi Yehuda hayu maalin miterumah leyuchsin. They would
assume that if somebody got תרומה terumah he was a כוהן kohen
and therefore they would marry him off. And therefore since that's their
assumption, you have to play into that assumption and you cannot can
only have כוהנים kohanim collect תרומה. terumah. במקומו של רבי יוסי לא
היו מעלין מתרומה ליוחסין. bimkomo shel Rabbi Yossi lo hayu maalin miterumah
leyuchsin. In רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yossi place they would assume no, you
could collect תרומה, terumah, maybe you're not a כוהן, kohen, maybe you're
an עבד, eved, and once that was the assumption and people wouldn't
therefore make assumptions that he's a כוהן, kohen, it's allowed for the
עבד eved to go and collect תרומה. terumah. תניא tanya we learned
in a ברייתא אמר רבי אלעזר בר צדוק amar Rabbi Elazar bar
Tzadok מימי לא העדתי אלא עדות אחת, miyamai lo headeti ela eidus
achas, I only in my life only gave one testimony, and and
that testimony was such a mistake that on the basis of it
it was accurate but as a result of it והעלו עבד לכהונה
על פי. vehe'elu eved lekehunah al pi. They decided that a slave
was a כוהן. kohen. I testified that a certain man collected תרומה,
terumah, they all of a sudden decided that he was a כוהן
kohen and they married him off to a you know to a
ישראלית, Yisraelis, and it turned out that he was a slave. That'll
teach me for giving testimony. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says והעלו
סלקא דעתך? vehe'elu salka dachak? Do we really think that they that
this error could have befallen a you know רבי יוסי? Rabbi Yossi?
I'm sorry, could have befallen רבי אלעזר בר צדוק? Rabbi Elazar bar
Tzadok? השתא בבהמתן של צדיקים אין הקדוש ברוך הוא מביא תקלה על
ידם. hashta bivehemtan shel tzaddikim ein Hakadosh Baruch Hu meivi takala al
yadam. If God doesn't allow even the animals of righteousness to do
something wrong, like you know the donkey of פנחס בן יאיר Pinchas
ben Yair wouldn't eat טבל tevel or whatever, צדיקים עצמן לא כל
שכן? tzaddikim atzman lo kol shekein? How much more so would He
not allowed that this testimony would have led to this terrible thing?
אלא אימא ביקשו להעלות עבד לכהונה על פי. ela eima bikshu lehaalos
eved lekehunah al pi. They almost, they were about to treat this
person as a כוהן kohen על פי al pi and and and
and then somehow the you know the facts came out. So the
גמרא changed the story that the actual thing didn't happen, but here's
the danger of assuming, hey I saw this guy collect תרומה, terumah,
some people will assume that means he's a כוהן kohen and in
some cases it's only he's an עבד. eved. And now the גמרא
will explain how this happened. Okay, what happened? חזה באתריה דרבי יוסי.
chaza be'asrei deRabbi Yossi. He saw this happen in רבי יוסי's Rabbi
Yossi place. In רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yose locale, and in רבי יוסי's
Rabbi Yose locale, עבדים avadim would collect תרומה terumah at the threshing
floor. So he said, hey, I saw this guy collect תרומה, terumah,
and he saw this in
רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yose locale, but he testified about it in רבי
יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda place. And in רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda place, oh,
you saw the guy collect תרומה, terumah, he must be a כהן,
kohen, because in רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda place they would only give
כהנים kohanim תרומה, terumah, they would not give עבדי כהנים avdei kohanim
תרומה. terumah. Okay, we will end here. We basically caught up. Good
job. All right, even starting ten minutes late and with our
small...